Guide to the Muslims in Brooklyn oral histories 2018.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Oral History Interview with Ahmed Nasser, September 18, 2018; 2018.006.40
  Arabs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Detectives -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religion in the workplace -- New York (State) -- New York; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; Yemenis -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Red Hook (New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Moustafa Bayoumi, September 25, 2018; 2018.006.41
  Moustafa Bayoumi was born in 1966 in Zürich, Switzerland. His family immigrated to Canada when he was a toddler and settled in Kingston, Ontario, where his parents taught at the local college. He moved to New York City in 1990 to attend graduate school at Columbia University. After earning his doctor of philosophy, he taught postcolonial literature at Brooklyn College. He was a prolific author on issues surrounding Islam and the Arab world, regularly appearing in The Guardian, The Progressive, and other similar publications. He also wrote the books How Does It Feel to Be a Problem?: Being Young and Arab in America in 2008 and This Muslim American Life: Dispatches from the War on Terror in 2015.
  In this interview, Moustafa Bayoumi discusses growing up in an Egyptian academic family in Kingston, Ontario. He expands on his own studies, especially pursuing his PhD at Columbia University; teaching at Brooklyn College; and becoming an author. He also speaks about American politics and law enforcement, especially surrounding the surveillance of Muslim American students at Brooklyn College; racial profiling in New York City; the consistent presence of Islamophobia throughout both Democratic and Republican presidential administrations; and the escalation in Islamophobia he has observed during the Trump administration. In addition, he touches on the broader demographic changes and gentrification in Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Arabs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; College teachers -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Gentrification -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 2016; Brooklyn College; Columbia University
- Oral History Interview with Su'ad Abdul Khabeer, September 26, 2018; 2018.006.42
  Su'ad Abdul Khabeer was born in 1978 and raised in the Crown Heights and Flatbush neighborhoods of Brooklyn. She earned her bachelor of science in foreign service from Georgetown University in Washington, D.C.; her diploma in Arabic and Islamic studies from Abu Nour University in Damascus, Syria; and her doctor of philosophy in cultural anthropology from Princeton University in Princeton, New Jersey. She examined the relationship between race and popular culture as an author and a performer, including publishing Muslim Cool: Race, Religion, and Hip Hop in the United States in 2016 and ongoing performances of Sampled: Beats of Muslim Life. She also joined the faculty at the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor in 2011 as a professor of American Culture and Arab and Muslim American Studies.
  In this interview, Su'ad Abdul Khabeer discusses her childhood in the Crown Heights and Flatbush neighborhoods of Brooklyn, including her family and her experiences at Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah and Masjid At-Taqwa, both in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. She expands on her religious and secular education, especially at Al-Madrasa Al-Islamiya in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn and at Edward R. Murrow High School in the Midwood neighborhood of Brooklyn. She speaks about her work on the intersection of race and culture, particularly regarding her performance piece Sampled: Beats of Muslim Life, and teaching at the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor. She also touches on gentrification in Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; African Americans in popular culture; African American women educators -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Gentrification -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hip-hop -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam and the performing arts; Islamic education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim educators -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Midwood (New York, N.Y.); Racism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religion and culture -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Mahmoud Widdi, September 27, 2018; 2018.006.43
  Mahmoud Widdi was born in 1957 in Beit Hanina during a period of changing political boundaries. He was raised primarily by his mother and paternal grandfather, and joined his father, Subhi Widdi, in the United States in 1975. He and his cousin opened a Met Foodmarket grocery store in the Prospect Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1983, which they converted into a Foodtown in 2016. He and his wife maintain strong connections to their Palestinian heritage, regularly visiting Beit Hanina and the surrounding area with their children.
  In this interview, Mahmoud Widdi discusses being raised in Beit Hanina, Palestine by his mother and grandfather; his personal experiences with violence and political upheaval in the region; and his thoughts about the conflict moving forward. He expands on his parents' relationship; his father's emigration from Palestine; and his own immigration to the United States as a young adult. He speaks at length about his father's involvement in the assisted living facility St. Nicholas Home in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn; his founding of Widdi Catering Hall; and the community effort to co-name the block the catering hall is located on "Subhi Widdi Way" after his death. Mahmoud also talks about working in his father's grocery stores; opening a Met Foodmarket in the Prospect Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn; and his marriage to his wife and their children. Interview conducted by Svetlana Kitto.
  Arab-Israeli conflict; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Family-owned business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Gentrification -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Grocery trade -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrant business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Israel-Arab War, 1967; Muslim families; Palestinian Arabs; Small businesses -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Bayt Ḥanīnā; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Israel; Palestine; Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Kameelah Rasheed, October 1, 2018; 2018.006.44
  Kameelah Rasheed was born in 1985 in East Palo Alto, California. She was raised in religiously diverse communities by an African American family who embraced Islam shortly after her birth. She attended both undergraduate and graduate school in California, earning a bachelor of the arts from Pomona College in Claremont and a master of education from Stanford University, and spent a year in South Africa as an Amy Biehl Fulbright Scholar. She moved to Brooklyn in 2010 and worked as a visual artist, exhibiting work at a variety of New York cultural institutions.
  In this interview, Kameelah Rasheed discusses growing up in East Palo Alto, California, especially regarding her interfaith group of friends, her parents' Muslim faith, and a series of family health crises while she was in college. She speaks about studying in South Africa for a year on a Fulbright scholarship, attending graduate school at Stanford University in California, and teaching in both California and Brooklyn. She elaborates on her exploration of her faith and experiences with Muslim communities in California, South Africa, and Brooklyn. She also talks at length about her philosophy and identity as an African American Muslim artist. In addition, she describes her relationship with her husband. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  African American Muslims; Communities -- Religious aspects -- Muslims; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fulbright scholars -- South Africa; Health -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Islam -- Prayers and devotions; Islam and art; Multiculturalism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim artists; Religious education of children; Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid At-Taqwa (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Rasheed, Kameelah
- Oral History Interview with Fatima Shama, October 2, 2018; 2018.006.45
  In this interview, Fatima Shama discusses her work in healthcare advocacy with the Greater Brooklyn Health Coalition and with New York City Mayor Michael Bloomberg's administration. She expands on her interactions with Mayor Bloomberg, building connections between Muslim New Yorkers and local government officials, and her memories of early efforts in the campaign to add the Eid holidays to the local public school calendar. She also touches on her feelings about the religiously-motivated surveillance by the New York Police Department and about her work going forward. Fatima Shama was also interviewed on September 17, 2018 for this collection. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Civil service -- New York (State) -- New York; Education of children -- New York (State) -- New York; Health services accessibility -- New York (State) -- New York; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- New York; Multiculturalism -- New York (State) -- New York; Muslims -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- New York; Palestinian Americans -- New York (State) -- New York; Women in community organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; New York (N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Faiza Ocasio, October 6, 2018; 2018.006.46
  Faiza Ocasio was born in 1953 in New York City. She was raised in a Catholic Puerto Rican family in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She married her husband and reverted to Islam while studying at Fordham University in the Bronx. After receiving their degrees, they moved to Washington, D.C. to work with the Islamic Party of North America. They returned to New York two years later, settling in the Cypress Hills neighborhood of Brooklyn. She became active in several Islam-centered organizations, including Alianza Islámica, a Latinx activist organization co-founded by her husband; Islamic Family Services in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, which offered support services for Muslim children in foster care in Brooklyn; and Al-Madrassa Al-Islamiya, a school in Staten Island and Brooklyn. She retired in 2015 and moved to Westminster, Maryland in 2016 to live on the family's farm.
  In this interview, Faiza Ocasio discusses growing up in a Catholic Puerto Rican family in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She speaks extensively about her Muslim faith, including her initial exploration of Islam, Latin Americans' ancestral roots in the religion through the Muslim conquest of Spain in the Middle Ages, and the relationship between her Muslim faith and Latinx heritage. She also remembers organizations that she has been involved with, with particular emphasis on the Islamic Party of North America in Washington, D.C.; teaching at Al-Madrasa Al-Islamiya in Staten Island and Brooklyn; and serving as Chief Fiscal Officer with Brooklyn-based Islamic Family Services prior to the agency's closure over its Chief Executive Officer's financial mismanagement. In addition, she talks about her relationship with her husband and buying a farm in Westminster, Maryland. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Agriculture -- Maryland -- Westminster; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Education of children -- New York (State) -- New York; Faith-based human services -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hispanic Americans -- New York (State) -- New York; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); Muslim converts from Christianity -- New York (State) -- New York; Puerto Rican Catholics -- New York (State) -- New York; Religious education of children -- New York (State) -- New York
- Oral History Interview with Maha Attieh, October 8, 2018; 2018.006.47
  Maha Attieh was born in 1958 in Amman, Jordan. She immigrated to the United States in 1981 and raised her five children in the Midwood neighborhood of Brooklyn. She began working at the Arab American Family Support Center in 2003 to improve Arab Americans' access to healthcare, particularly among non-English speakers. Her commitment to providing Arab American communities with health and education services also led to her becoming involved with other initiatives in New York City, including the State University of New York Downstate Medical Center community outreach committee; the New York Immigration Coalition; the New York City Language Access Committee; and the Khalil Gibran International Academy in Brooklyn.
  In this interview, Maha Attieh talks about immigrating to the United States; settling in the Midwood neighborhood of Brooklyn; and raising her five children. She expands on her involvement in her children's education, particularly following the September 11 Terrorist Attacks in 2001, and on her son's military service in Iraq. She speaks at length about her work in healthcare with the Arab American Family Support Center. She also touches on Americanization, Islamophobia, and changes she has seen in Arab American communities since settling in Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Americanization; Arabs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Health services accessibility -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamic religious education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; Veterans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women political activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Amman (Jordan); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Midwood (New York, N.Y.); Arab American Family Support Center, Inc. (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Stacey Salimah-Bell, October 9, 2018; 2018.006.48
  Stacey Salimah-Bell was born in 1963 in Brooklyn. She was raised in the Bensonhurst neighborhood of Brooklyn. She spent more than twenty years working for the New York City Department of Correction, eventually rising to the rank of Captain. She was involved in a successful class action lawsuit against the New York City Department of Corrections for sexual harassment. She was a founding member of the American Muslim Law Enforcement Officers Association in 2001 and Muslims Employed in City Corrections Association, Inc. in 2006. She also served as Vice President for the Afro-American Historical and Genealogical Society Jean Sampson Scott Greater New York Chapter.
  In this interview, Stacey Salimah-Bell discusses her family, particularly regarding their relocation to New York City during the Great Migration; her memories of her grandmother; and her relationship with her husband. She speaks at length about her tenure in the New York City Department of Correction, including the successful class action lawsuit she joined over sexual harassment; her efforts to secure accommodations for religious clothing; being a founding members of the American Muslim Law Enforcement Officers Association and Muslims Employed in City Corrections Association, Inc.; and being at Ground Zero during the September 11 terrorist attack in 2001. She expands on converting to Islam as a young woman; attending Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah; and changes in the her religious beliefs and practices over time. She also talks about her work with the Girl Scouts. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Class actions (Civil procedure) -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing and dress -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Correctional institutions -- New York (State) -- New York; Correctional personnel -- New York (State) -- New York; Hijab (Islamic clothing) -- New York (State) -- New York; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- New York; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Muslim converts from Christianity -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religion and culture; Religion in the workplace -- New York (State) -- New York; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; Sexual harassment in law enforcement -- New York (State) -- New York; Sexual harassment of women -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- New York; Girl Scouts of the United States of America; Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Shaheen Rushd, October 17, 2018; 2018.006.49
  Shaheen Rushd was born in 1956 in Chittagong, Pakistan (now Bangladesh), and came to the United States in 1970 when her father was stationed in Washington, D.C. as a diplomat. When her parents returned to the newly-independent Bangladesh, she remained in the United States to complete high school, and went on to attend Kalamazoo College in Michigan and New York Law School. After earning her law degree, she joined a Manhattan law firm that specialized in securities litigation. She and her husband raised their children in the Cobble Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn, and upon retirement, she became involved in local social justice organizations and in the Democratic Party.
  In this interview, Shaheen Rushd discusses her family's history in religious, academic, and political circles in South Asia, as well as her own upbringing in a secular Bengali Muslim household. She speaks about her father's diplomatic assignment to Washington, D.C. and their experience of the Bangladesh War of Independence from the United States. She elaborates about attending high school near Washington, D.C., her experiences at Kalamazoo College in Michigan, and her work as a lawyer. In addition, she talks about her decades-long residence in the Brooklyn Heights and Cobble Hill neighborhoods of Brooklyn; her interfaith marriage with her Jewish husband; their children's relationship with their Bengali heritage and Jewish religious traditions; and her own exploration of Islam. She puts significant emphasis on her political activism following the 2016 presidential election, particularly involving her membership in the Kings County Democratic Committee; economic inequality and gentrification; and segregation in schools. She also repeatedly touches on her lifelong experiences around diversity, racial profiling, misogyny, and class throughout the interview. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Bangladesh; Bangladesh -- History -- Revolution, 1971; Bengali Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Diversity in the workplace -- New York (State) -- New York; Education, Secondary -- Washington, D.C.; Gentrification -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Interfaith families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Interracial marriage -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamophobia -- United States; Multiculturalism -- United States; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 2016; Segregation in education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; South Asian Americans -- United States; Washington (D.C.); Women lawyers -- New York (State) -- New York; Women political activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County
- Oral History Interview with Linda Sarsour, October 17, 2018; 2018.006.50
  Linda Sarsour was born in 1980 in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. Following the September 11 Terrorist Attacks in 2001, she became involved with the newly-founded Arab American Association of New York (AAANY) as both an organizer and a certified Arabic interpreter. She succeeded co-founder Basemah Atweh as executive director of the AAANY in 2005. During her tenure in the AAANY, she became involved in a number of progressive causes, particularly in defense of Arab American and African American communities. During the 2016 presidential election, she campaigned first for Senator Bernie Sanders in the Democratic primary and then for Democratic nominee Secretary Hillary Clinton in the general election. When Republican Donald Trump was elected instead, she took an active role in resisting his administration, including co-chairing the Women's March on Washington in 2017 in protest of his inauguration, which attracted millions of participants nationwide.
  In this interview, Linda Sarsour discusses growing up in the Sunset Park and Crown Heights neighborhoods of Brooklyn, especially regarding her Palestinian American family; her education at John Jay High School in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn; and her memories of the September 11 Terrorist Attacks in 2001. She expands on her involvement with the Arab American Association of New York, including her experiences as a female leader in patriarchal communities; her close personal relationships with co-founders Ahmed Jaber (interviewed for this collection on January 24, 2018) and Basemah Atweh; and Basemah Atweh's death in a car accident in 2005. She also speaks at length about her political activism, particularly surrounding intersectionality, racial justice, and the 2016 presidential election. She expands on her work with Carmen Perez, Tamika Mallory, and Bob Bland to organize the Women's March on Washington in 2017 to protest the election of Republican Donald Trump. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Arab Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Black lives matter movement; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Children of immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Intersectionality (Sociology); Political activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 2016; Race relations -- United States; Religious pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; Women, Palestinian Arab; Women in Islam; Women in community organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jaber, Ahmad; Arab American Association of New York
- Oral History Interview with Abdul Hafeez Muhammad, October 21, 2018; 2018.006.51
  Abdul Hafeez Muhammad was born in 1963 in New York City. He was raised in the Canarsie neighborhood of Brooklyn. As a teenager, he spent time in the Five Percent Nation before becoming involved in the Nation of Islam. He became the assistant minister of Muhammad Mosque No. 7 in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1984; the minister of the newly-founded Muhammad Mosque No. 7C in the Brownsville of Brooklyn in 1993; and the minister of Muhammad Mosque No. 7A in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan in 2000. He was also an activist within the broader Black community, including co-chairing the local organizing committee for the Million Man March in Washington, D.C. in 1995.